A Guide to the Irvine-Saunders Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #116
Irvine-Saunders Family Papers 1745-1910 Inclusive
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
Collection number 116
2100 items
Collector: William H. Irvine
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection (# 116 ) was loaned to the Library by William H. Irvine of Evington, Virginia on September 15, 1938.
Scope and Content
This collection, 1745-1910, n.d., of ca. 2100 items, consists of correspondence, business and legal papers, miscellaneous, and bound volumes, pertaining to the Davis Family, Saunders Family, and Watts Family. Large portions of the correspondence belong to William Watts and Fleming Saunders. Included with the correspondence is a letterbook, 1873-1880, of Frank Prufer. The business papers include accounts, bonds, correspondence, and notes and receipts, chiefly pertaining to William Watts and Fleming Saunders, but also various members of these families. The legal papers include court dockets and memoranda of William Watts, documents, and wills. There are various legal papers of William Watts pertaining to Virginia counties including Amelia County, Amherst County, Buckingham County, Campbell County, Cumberland County, Prince Edward County. The miscellaneous material includes advertisements, educational papers, photographs, printed, religious papers, and fragments. The bound volumes include day books, a blacksmith book, a farm journal, memorandum books, and a township record. Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series, with material inside arranged chronologically.
Correspondence
From the correspondence of the Davis Family, Saunders Family, and related families, 1800-1856, there is a letter addressed to "Sully," December 30, 1800, from Louisa County, which advises the recipient, who had asked for religious instruction, to seek the Kingdom of God. A letter dated April 2, 1812 from James Rayland to his sister mentions that his cousin is strapped for cash, and asks if the recipient can help him. A rather unusual letter, dating July 24, 1836, from Mount Pleasant, indicates that "Mary thinks a little Brandy would be of service to her," and requests that some be sent to her. A letter written to Captain Davis on January 9, 1844, mentions that Pleasant Milkhill needs brandy, and asks that it be sent with David(probably a slave) for there is none at Bethel. A letter dating November 6, 1856 at Bleak Hills makes a reference to "Roanoke" [Roanoke County, or John Randolph's estate "Roanoke"?].
From their correspondence dating 1862-1904, there is a letter to Sam Tyree, Esq, July 17, 1870 from [his] student: [Sam L. Preston?] complaining that he can not attend sunday school because of prostration. There is also a letter dated April 8, 1901 from Trinity and Ivy Chapel in Boonsboro, Bedford County to a Mr. Randolph inviting him to preach there every other Sunday. There is also an undated fragment referring to a comet the size of a full moon and a meteor shower which "will be a sight to see."
Among the families' undated correspondence, is a letter dated November 17 to "Carter" [Saunders?], by a female who mentions [her] children's Latin lessons. There is another letter to a Miss Kerr which mentions a recipe for Tongue a la Mode. There is also a letter, dated October 23, [1805?], from a Sam K. Jenny, probably a doctor of medicine, which mentions that William Green attended a man named Barnhart to Bedford so Jenny could prescribe to his case and that he "forbad the case of ardent spirits."
From the correspondence of Eva (Smith) Saunders, dated 1868-1894, there is a letter, February 24, 1889, from The Grove which mentions that while Eva passed her exams--her brother Fleming Saunders III did not. A letter, August 2, 1892, to Eva Saunders from M. Natalie Manson, at Wintore, speaks of school and Latin. There is an interesting letter, December 10, 1893, from Florence, Italy to Eva, mentioning that there is no silver in Italy for the English and French are buying it up, that "Coppers are such a bother, and so heavy to carry," seeing the works of Donato and Brunelleschi and the Medici Chapel, and the "Brothers of Pity" who wear black robes and carry a corpse which "made my blood turn cold." There is a letter, January 13, 1894, to Eva, which mentions sending a book to May Begg, "a literary courtship under the auspices of Pike's Peak. " Fleming Saunders III at Randolph-Macon Academy in Bedford writes to Eva on May 15, 1894, saying he tried to get a tennis tournament for field day, and congratulates Eva on her chicken raising and hopes his are doing better.
Among the Eva Saunders undated correspondence, there is a fragment which notes that Miss Begg sent to its writer a little book called "The greatest thing in the World." A letter dated November 26 to Eva contains drawings of women's blouses and concerns her ordered blouses.
From the correspondence of Fleming Saunders and Mary (Gwathmey) Saunders, 1858-1879, a letter dated September 5, 1871, from Peter Saunders, Jr., Bleak Hill, says that his tobacco crop has suffered. Another letter, April 17, 1874, from Jeanie Edmond, Hudson Lodge, makes a reference to the Jubilee Singers traveling to raise money for a "slave college somewhere in the Northern States"; to acquaintances visiting England, mentioning a "public worship bill" in Parliament, and one acquaintance having an appointment with the Bishop of Melbourne; and to visiting Australia. In a postcard dated August 21, 1879, W. A. Alrich asks Fleming Saunders' opinion as to the next "services" in "regular course," and saying that it best not to alter rotation as "last service was omitted." He also mentions that Mrs. C[harles] Dabney has a fine little daughter.
In the Fleming and Mary Saunders correspondence, 1880-1892, there is a letter dated March 3, 1880 from M. Caden to Saunders stating that he can not board a minister, but will give the same salary as before. Peter Saunders writes from Bleak Hill on January 19, 1881 saying that he has no specific desire to be a director on the Virgina Midland [Rail] Road, and does not think he could get the appointment anyway; he is still a director on the Franklin and Pittsylvania Railroad Company, and fears a possible conflict of interest. W. A. Alrich writes from Emanuel Rectory, Chatham, Virginia, on February 16, 1882, saying he is glad that the Saunders' keep up the old St. Valentine's Day tradition, by sending so practical a token of affection. Ellen Boulder, a school teacher, writes to Mary Saunders from Drake's Branch on March 18, 1889, mentioning a five month school term ending on March 1st and a June 23 to July 23 summer session. [Peter Saunders], Bleak Hill, writes Fleming Saunders, on October 26, 1891 mentioning Republican elements in the "alliance" [farmers' alliance such as the Grange?].
In the Fleming and Mary Saunders correspondence, 1893-1900, Fleming Saunders III writes to his parents from Randolph-Macon Academy in Bedford on March 14, 1893, saying that he is in the Baptist Church in the morning and the Methodist in the afternoon, and tells of boys who spend more time with the girls than studying. James F. Plummer writes to Captain Saunders on March 29, 1893, [from a theological seminary?], saying that exams are beginning, and implying that knowledge of Hebrew and Apologetics will be next among those things tested. Peter Saunders writes to Fleming from Bleak Hill, on March 30, 1894, mentioning the Bland Bill and the fear that its veto would cause discord in the Democratic Party, and discussing briefly possible effects on the present financial situation.
In the Fleming and Mary Saunders correspondence, 1901-1910, there is a letter, July 19, 1901, from Edward Watts Saunders, while serving in the Virginia House of Delegates. William W. Old writes to Fleming on February 2, 1903 about a land sale and his agreement to sell the land as a whole parcel to two black men, and suggesting a method of finalizing the transaction. E. W. Saunders writes to Fleming on January 21, 1904 mentioning an inquiry about his land near "Vic. Muse." A letter, [March 1904], from Alice [Saunders] at Hollins, Virginia, to her aunt Saunders refers to the Roman poet Virgil. She writes to her mother on March 12, 1904 mentioning that John [ ] had failed in Caesar and that he had been in the second book of Virgil.
In the undated Fleming and Mary Saunders correspondence, D. Saunders writes to his mother from Randolph-Macon Academy on February 10, saying that he is learning German and is plagued by poor spelling, and that the boys dance every night and were previously boxing.
In the correspondence of William Watts, 1754-1784, there is a letter dated June 27, 1771 which summons Watts to the General Assembly in Williamsburg. Samuel Dilworth writes on June 2, 1783 from Blanford mentioning the problem of collecting debts owed to the British. Thomas Baldwin, Jr. writes on December 22, 1784 concerning the purchase of "the Negro Fellow" for $18.
In the Watts correspondence, 1785-1789, a letter, December 16, 1785, from William Roach informs Watts that while Peter Kern is employing Watts in a matter between Kern and Roach, Watts is to plead for Roach in all matters, suggesting a conflict of interest. Arthur Campbell, a candidate for the senate from the Western Distict, writes, on March 24, 1788, asking for Watts' support. Edward Graham of Bedford, writes on December 20, 1792, mentioning that he saw the Watts' son reading Horace and sending the boy a copy of Cicero which would supply "the means of raising him as high in eminence as you could reasonably wish," and adding that the boy will need to learn Greek as he will soon be studying science.
In the Watts correspondence, 1793-1794, Duncan Rose writes from Petersburg, on July 8, 1794, stating that Buchanan's Hartie and Company has been doing business in Great Britain and is waiting for a successor to Hartie to be appointed before certain books could be examined by Rose. Another letter pertains to relations with France and Britain at this time: George Hancock writes to Watts in 1794 mentioning the rearing of a navy "to repel the insult to our ploy," referring to commerce restriction [on American goods] by a nation which does not have a commerce treaty with the U.S., and referring to Mr. [James] Madison's arguments whereas he conducted himself in a manner worthy of himself. Creed Taylor writes on May 11, 1795, concerning some bonds. William Vannerson writes, on October 30, 1795, from Petersburg mentioning a British war sloop in Norfolk, Virginia and the order for carrying American bottoms bound for France into British ports with invoice being revoked, revealing that some say that this retaliation has been brought about by Americans invoicing their flour at $27 per barrel.
In Watts' correspondence with Edward Randolph, 1796-1797, Randolph writes from Richmond on February 21 and March 13, 1796 on the subject of British creditors. In Watts' correspondence with Thomas F. Scott, 1792-1798, Scott writes on January 4, 1796 and December 18, 1798 on the subject of British debts. In the correspondence of William Watts with John Watts, 1784-1800, John writes to William in April 1784 from Lincoln County, Virginia(now Kentucky), concerning apprehension about a possible Indian war in the Northwest Territories. John says that while the lands in Kentucky are good, the inconveniences are many, and that the doomsayers will probably prevent the surveying of lands on the northwest side of the Ohio.
Business Papers
There are general accounts, 1751-1899, n.d. An account, beginning November 16, 1762, with George Kippen & Co. at their store in Goochland, Virginia, lists John Gilliam as having ordered a dozen flints, 3/4 yard of bearskin, and a dozen pipes. There is a list, April 20, 1763, pertaining to the estate of A. Watts, on which is listed a £0.2.0 debt to Mary Petillo, the only woman on the list, and a £2.4.9 debt to Sir William Skipwith. The account of Thomas East with Archelaus Austin from November 15, 1771, consists of beer, wine, grog, and a gallon of corn, with one entry "to saging one night" perhaps pertaining to the making of moonshine. An account, beginning January 20, 1775, of N[ ] Vaughn with Edward Watts lists various quantities of rum, molasses, and sugar. There are several accounts, 1779-1794, of the estate of Nathaniel Davis, including an entry for 1784 for three yards of woollen for a Negro jacket, and May 9, 1784 for half of hire of Jacob. There is a section, "Accts Overlooked," from 1784, which refers to tobacco being a share and half share for Jacob, and another for dinner at the courthouse when on business. There is an account of James Davis with Daniel Warwick, dating 1799-1803, with references to a variety of items including coffee, sewing materials, dinner ware, alcohol, and accessories. Mrs. Elizabeth Davis' account beginning May 31, 1807, has an entries for coffee, condiments, and sewing material. An account, March 26, 1810, of Capt. James Davis with Rowland P. Banks lists "163 days tuition at $8 p. ann. $5 cts 1 1/2." The account, beginning August 14, 1826, of Capt. James Davis with Thomas Pleasants, has lists orders for cheese, mackerel, cotton, and whiskey. On October 31, 1832, Judge Saunders, of Lynchburg, Virginia, orders castor oil, ointment, and a syringe. Accounts which mention tea are rare but there is an undated fragment of Mr. James Davis which contains an entry for imperial tea. There is an undated "memorandum of brandy" taken from Mrs. Eubank.
The accounts of Williams Watts span 1752-1797. There is also a hotel account with Charles Williamson with entries dating 1763, 1773, and 1774. There are accounts for the boarding, clothing, and feeding of Negro boys with Mrs. Betty Tucker and Betty Kirkland, both beginning September 10, 1767, and Capt. Joseph Tucker, 1767-1769. Watts has accounts, 1768, with John Brittan for a waistcoat, shoes, stockings, and a hat. There is a 1769 account for various building supplies. Watts also has an account, beginning April 20, 1771, with Miller Woodson with an entry of May 16, 1772 listing a Patrick Henry. There is a document which contains information on the estate of William Randolph. There is another lodging account, July 26, 1773 through December 3, 1776, of Watts with Charles Williams. There is an account beginning March 9, 1778, with William Kirkland which includes listings for tuition and educational books. A January 10, 1780 account with Frederick Nance mentions a violin and a set of strings. There is an account, beginning December 21, 1787, with Robert Wilson ordering Hyson Tea, coffee, and a bottle of snuff. From a 1791 account of Edward McDonald with William Watts, there is the note of the hire of a Negro. From a 1792 account of Charles Smith, there is a note for the finding of a Negro woman and for the inspecting of tobacco. There are two medical bills, one with George Martin, beginning January 14, 1794, and one with Doctor Graham, beginning November 3, 1795. In October 1797, Watts had an account with George Quille for the hire of a Negro. There is an undated account of W. Walter Spence with Watts for the hire of a Negro for eight months.
Promissory notes and receipts range from 1754-1905, n.d. There are several items concerned with the estate of John Fleming and include an entry for February 1764 for a Negro bought for $10. Between George Martin and Watts there is an agreement, October 3, 1794, mentioning the purchase of red wheat and the hire of a Negro woman. James Davis has a note dated 1803 with the Sheriff of Amherst County for tax on four Negroes, four horses, and five tithes. Elizabeth Davis has a note dated 1816 for tax on three Negroes and one horse. There is a note from December 6, 1827 pertaining to a $5 bond for the hire of a Negro man by James Davis from J. Wright for Lavinia Wright. There is a 1840 note from Charles Davis to the Sheriff of Amherst for tax on six Negroes and six horses.
Legal Papers
There are a number of court memoranda, 1768-1786, n.d., kept by William Watts in his capacity as a lawyer. In a November 10, 1771 memo for the Buckingham County court, there is an entry for detinue for Negro woman named Agge. From the memo for the April 1772 court at Lunenburg County, Thomas Taylor and his wife have a suit against a Hurt for a Negro in Amelia. There is also a list of debts owed to Watts for the year 1794. Dating 1771 through 1782, there are court dockets from Amelia County and Lunenburg County from 1771-1782. A number of the entries have Watts as the litigant. There is a 1773 day book with the signatures of William and Edward Watts, which includes a record of William Watts' court expenses. There are also legal day books, 1772-1773, of Watts, with entries for Buckingham County, Amelia, Cumberland County, and Prince Edward County as well as for Williamsburg, Virginia. There is another 1773 memorandum book of Watts with entries for Amelia County, Cumberland County, and Buckingham County.
The indentures date 1749-1788, n.d. From January 1, 1763, there is an agreement between Benjamin Tambro and Ayres Hodnett of Buckingham in regard to the former's son, John Tambro, to be apprentice to the latter for seven years. From March 28, 1774, there is an indenture between Watts and William Ford. From September 17, 1768, there is an agreement between Abraham West and John Blankenship of Prince Edward. On November 17, 1772, there is an agreement between John Lewallen of Amelia County and James and Robert Donalds and Company, Merchants of Glasgow. On September 15, 1778, there is an agreement between David Wright of Botetourt and Alexander Paine of the same concerning a land dispute in the area where the Roanoke River and Tinker Creek.
The will, December 25, 1745, of Thomas Patterson of Albemarle County, names his slaves and divides them among his children and wife, and requests that his land in Goochland County be known as "Locust Thicket."; Margery Hinshaw contested the will of Samuel Hinshaw dated March 1758 with [Cedw] Gibson on July 10, 1765. Hinshaw had divided his slaves between his still living wife, his daughter Elizabeth Hinshaw, and the latter's children. This situation involved a slave of Elizabeth. The will of Thomas Bottom of Amelia dated May 10, 1760 divides his slaves which are named between his three daughters.
A folder of general legal papers date 1765-1903, n.d. The inventory and appraisal, 1826, of the estate of John Eubank mentions prices for his Negroes: £300 for a man named Jacob, £200 for a man named Joe, £10 for a woman named Hannah, £20 for a girl named Lolly, and £0 for a girl named Caroline. There is also a list of tickets of ommission paid by William Watts, attorney. Among the legal papers of Amelia County, 1768 through 1789 including undated material, a document dated May 15, 1783 states that Sarah Tinker on December 6, 1781 gave her son-in-law John Tucker an ailing Negro named Ned until the latter gets well whereas he will be returned to Sarah Tucker. In an undated document, George Vaughn yields up title/right of two Negroes--named Frank and Phoebe--to son-in-law John Norris--formerly given to grandson John Norris by a deed dated October 2, 1796: "said slaves will forever defend me from my heirs." The son-in-law Norris will pay Vaughn or wife £10 annually for preformance of the aforesaid act. Among the Campbell County papers, Justice Adam Clement says that Charles Gilbert of Campbell on April 29, 1787 makes oath that Negro slave Jack--property of Watts of Prince Edward County--ran away and was found 50 miles thence. Among the legal papers of Prince Edward, Edward Watts sold to William Watts eight Negro slaves: True, James, Winnie, Peter, Sarah, Betty, Rachel, and Doc on January 14, 1787. There is also a account of Dr. M. John King with the sheriff of Lunenburg which has an entry dating 1769: the former is in account with [John] Epps for four lbs. of tobacco at £0.5.1.
Miscellaneous
Among the Advertisements there is an advertisement dated September 20, 1871 from the Omaha, Nebraska Lottery for the building of a public library in the city. A broadside from Cox and Sons Church Furniture shows a garish stained-glass window commemorating the late President James Garfield. There is an undated letter to Mrs. Fleming Saunders asking for a subscription to the Graphic, a ladies society magazine. There is an undated list of books from George Munro, Publishers. There is also a broadside for "The World's Christmas Hymn"--an analogy of English poetry pertaining to Christ's birth dating from the medieval period.
The church related papers include a letter, March 21, 1904, from Virginia Polytechnic Institute to the Saunders asking for aid for the building of an Episcopal parsonage at the university. The letter enunciates a fear of the danger of Episcopal boys being weaned from their faith by the compulsory attendance at the services of other sects due to the absence of a Episcopal parsonage. There is also an Episcopal "Church Kalendar," 1882-1883, listing holy days with information on the faith, church service, and background of the Anglican/Episcopalian faith.
Civil War papers range from 1861 to 1864. During 1862-1864, there are a number of furloughs issued to Confederate enlisted men in Virginia, each with a physical description of the bearer, and addressed "to all whom it may concern." On August 10, 1862, there is a provision return for a company of the 13th Regiment of Pennsylvania volunteers. There are also a number of CSA "special requisitions", chiefly ordering clothing, shoes, and blankets, most signed by Captain Fleming Saunders, assistant quartermaster, of Company K, Virginia Regiment.
The educational papers range from 1848-1903, n.d. There is a page from a 1848 French edition of the fables of La Fontaine from the "Academie de Norfolk." There is an "Educational Treatise on the Constitution", September 6, 1877, by John Randolph Tucker of Virginia. There is a 1892-1893 brochure for the Edgeworth School, a church-related boarding and day school for females. There is the fall term 1895 grade report from Virginia Polytechnic Institute(formerly Virginia Agriculture and Mechanical College) for Fleming Saunders, III. There is a fall term 1902 grade report from Hollins College for Elsie Saunders. There is another VPI grade report, from February 1903, for Carter Temple Saunders. There is a report from St. Timothy's School of Catonsville, Maryland. Another undated piece is a "rules for spelling" sheet from a grammar book. There are also undated fragments of Latin, French, and algebra.
There are lectures, essays, and poems, 1794, 1818, 1843, and n.d., including a scrap of a lecture dated September 6, 1794 from Edward Watts; another lecture on motive dated September 16, 1794; and, a series of oral essays from 1843.
Miscellaneous material, 1887-1892, includes a note of the marriage of Capt. Fleming Saunders to Mary Gwathmey on July 30.
The obituaries include a reprint of the 1858 obituary of Fleming Saunders, Sr, a reprint of the 1867 obituary of Fleming, Sr.'s wife-- Alice Fleming--and the 1904 obituary of Peter Saunders. The obituaries of Fleming, Sr. and Alice are panegyrics. The first two were transcribed by John Blair Dabney.
The photographs include an unidentified photograph of a young member of the Saunders family and undated photo cards of liturgical furniture.
Bound Volumes